好的，谢谢你回来。
Okay. Thanks for coming back.
嗯，我们开始吧。
Yeah, let's get started.
好的，关于报名的最新情况。
Cool. Enrollment updates.
我们已经发出了两批邀请。
We have sent out two batches of invitations.
一批在周三，另一批在周四。
One on Wednesday, the other on Thursday.
我觉得我们会再尝试招收100名学生。
I think we try to enroll another 100 students.
如果你想参加这门课，你需要接受邀请。
And if you want to take this class, you need to accept.
你有24小时的截止时间。
You have a 24 hours due.
截止后，我们将在明天早上招收下一批学生。
After the deal, we are going to enroll the next batch tomorrow morning.
好的，明白了。
Yeah. Okay.
嗯，我们开始今天的内容吧。
Um, let's get started with today's contents.
我把那张图表放在那里，是为了确保你们明白自己现在处于什么位置。
So I put that graph there so make sure you understand where you are now.
明白了吗？我们现在在最底层，好吗？
Okay? Well, at the bottom layer, okay?
运算符。上一节课，
Operators. So last lecture,
我们开始讨论了如何让运算符整体上变得更快，对吧？
I think we start talking about how to make operators fast in general, right?
我们说可以通过利用平台上的矢量化函数来实现矢量化，
And we said we can vectorize them by leveraging the torized functions from platforms,
加速平台。
accelerator platforms.
我们还涉及了数据布局，但还没有讲完。
And we also touch based on data layout and haven't finished yet.
好，今天我们会把这个讲完，然后我们还会讨论
Okay. Today we are going to finish that, and then we are going to talk about
一个非常非常深入的话题。
something that is very, very deep.
这就是我们的第一节元学习课程。
And that is our first metam lesson.
好吗？我们会有很多很多这样的课程，但今天我们先上第一节。
Okay? We are going to have many, many these lessons, but today we are going to take the first.
如果我们能完成这一部分，然后我们会讨论一些
And if we can finish it part, and then we are going to talk about something
非常有趣的话题，那就是当前的GPO市场。
that's really interesting that is the current GPO market.
我们会把那节课改成经济学课程。
We are going to repurpose that class as a economics class.
我们试着去理解硅谷正在发生什么，好吗？
We try to understand what's going on in Silicon Valley. Okay?
好的，我们继续讲数据布局。
Yeah, let's resume with data layout.
嗯，还记得这个吧，对吧？
Um, so still remember this one, right?
所以比起部署框架，他们基本上使用的是稀疏格式。
So more than deploying frameworks, they basically use stress format.
和列主序或行主序相比，我们引入了另外两个参数。
We like compared to column major or row major, we introduce two more parameters.
一个是偏移，对吧？
One is offset, right?
另一个是步长，它是一个列表，维度等于张量的形状。
The other is the stress, which is a list, okay with a dimension equal to the shape of the tensor.
这个可视化基本上给你一个关于步长的概念，好吗？
And this visualization basically give you a concept of what does strat means, okay?
我们还做了一个很小的练习，如果我们有一个四维张量
And we also did a very small exercise, if we have a four dimensional tensor
形状是1、2、3、4。
with a shape one, two, three, four.
那步长是什么？
So what stress?
我希望你们真的理解了这一点，好吗？
I hope you guys actually understand that. Okay?
然后我们开始问这样一个问题，列主序和行主序其实都挺好的。
And then we start asking the question, column major and row major are actually pretty good.
那为什么我们在保存张量时还要关心步长呢？
Why do we care about saving stress when saving tensors?
为了回答这个问题，
So in order to answer this question,
我想你们大多数人在编写petard或程序时，可能经常会用到这个API view。
I think most of you when you write petard or programs, you probably often use this API view.
你可以用不同的形状查看一个张量。
You can view a tensor in different shapes.
例如，原始形状是一、二、三、四，
For example, the original shape is one, two, three, four,
但你也可以把它看作24乘1之类的，对吧？
but you can view it as 24 by one or something, right?
我们之所以有这个“view”，是因为它可以方便很多这类
And the reason we have this stress because it can facilitate a lot of this kind
数组操作算子的实现。
of array manipulation operators.
而view就是这样一个例子。
And view is such an example.
嗯，这里的核心概念是view可以把底层存储和view张量分开。
Um, the core concept here is stress can separate the underlying storage and the view tensor.
所以基本上，当我们存储数组的值时，都是按顺序存储在内存中的。
So basically when we store the values of the ray, we are always stored sequentially in memory.
但我们可以用很多很多不同的方式来看它。
But we can view it in many many different ways.
嗯，因为这个原因，每当我们尝试以不同的方式、不同的形状查看测试时，
And, um, and because of this, we can basically every time we try to view
我们不需要复制内容。
the test in a different shape in a different way, we don't have to copy the content.
我们不需要从原始数组中复制内容，
We don't have to copy the content from the original array in
到内存的另一个部分。
the lower level memory into another part of the memory.
我们只需要对这种操作符进行零拷贝即可。
We just need to we can do a zero copy for this kind of operators.
明白了吗？接下来的几页幻灯片里，
Okay? And in the next few slides,
我会给你展示一些你用来操作数组的非常常见的操作符。
I'm going to show you some very common operators you use to manipulate arrays.
我还会告诉你，实际上在petrich中这些操作符都是零拷贝的。
And I'm going to tell you, actually, in petrich there or zero copy.
也就是说，当你执行这类操作符时，你不需要复制任何东西。
That is when you perform this kind of operators, you don't have to copy anything.
没有任何额外开销，非常快，明白吗？
It's zero overhead, very fast, okay?
所有这些基本上都可以归因于这种应力格式，好吗？
And all this could contribute basically attribute to this stress format, okay?
当我操作之前，我希望你先花点时间思考一下如何实现这个，当
When I preoperat I want you to first spin off your second to think about how to implement that when
我给你这个应力格式时。
I give you this stress format.
第一个是切片，我们如何对张量进行切片？
The first one slice, how we can slice the tensor?
比如说，这里我有一个四乘四的张量，也就是四乘四的矩阵，我想要切出其中一部分。
For example, here, I have four by four tensor four by four matrix, and I want to slice that piece.
最简单的方法，你可能就是把那部分内容复制到另一个数组里
So rudimentary way, you probably just copy that pyro content into another array
然后你就得到了那一部分。但我们不想进行复制。
and you get that one. But we don't want to copy.
所以有一种方法是我们可以直接操作应力和偏移量的值。
So one way to do that is we can just manipulate the values of the stress and offset.
所以我们首先把偏移量加一，对吧？
So we first add the offset by one, right?
然后我们把形状重新写成三乘二，并且传递这个偏移量和形状
And then we rewrite the shape into three by two, and we pass this offset and shape
输入应力和偏移值后，你基本上可以从这个更大的张量中切片出你需要的传感器。
into the stress and offset values, and you basically can slice the sensor
从这个更大的张量中切出来。明白了吗？
out from this bigger tenser. Okay? Does that make sense?
很好。
Cool.
我觉得这里我想强调的关键点是复制。
I think the key part here I want to make is the copy.
基本上，切片后的张量和原始张量是共享内存的。
Basically, the sliced tensor, it shares memory with this original tensor.
但你依然会得到一个形状不同的新张量，对吧？
But you still get a kind of a new tensor that with a different shape, right?
切片是一个很常见的操作符，但另一个非常常见的操作符是转置。
And slice is a pretty common operator, but another very common operator is transpose.
这里，我觉得大家都明白转置或置换的操作。
Here, I think everyone understands trasposeOPermute.
所以这里你有一个原始形状为2乘3的张量。
So here you have a tensor with original shape of two by three.
你想把它转置成一个3乘2的张量。
You want to transpose it into a three by two.
这怎么做呢？好，我们来看一下，我们可以通过一个非常非常简单的例子来演示。
How does that? Okay, let's see, we can run through a very, very simple example.
这里我有一个四维的张量，然后我直接打印它的应力。
So here I have a tensor four dimensional tensor, and I directly print it stress.
就像我们在上一节课说的，应力基本上就是24 12 4 1，对吧？
And as we said in the last lecture, the stress is basically 24 12 for one, right?
然后这个permute基本上就是转置，但它是在高维空间里的，好吗？
And then this permute is basically, uh transpose but it's in high dimensional, okay?
当我们尝试对维度进行permute时，基本上就是把第一个维度移到最后，
And we try to permute the dimension, we basically shift the first dimension to the end,
然后把接下来的三个维度都往前移一个位置，好吗？
and we put the next three dimensions one position ahead, okay?
你可以看到，如果我们打印permute后的值，底层的存储其实还是一样的，对吧？
And you can see if we print the permuted value, the underlying storage is still the same, right?
顺序上还是从1一直到23，从那里到一直到23。
Sequentially from one all the way to 23 from there to all the way to 23.
但这里发生变化的是，我们其实对应力做了一点点修改，对吧？
But what changes here is basically we kind of modify the stress a little bit, right?
但只是修改了应力。
But only modifying the stress.
记住，张量是分散的值，不会占用太多内存空间。
Remember stress is a scatter values not going to be a lot of memory spaces.
你只需要修改一个小的数值，其实就可以实现这种转置。
You just need to modify a small value, and you can actually achieve this kind of transpose.
实际上，在所有的petroloNpi中，当你做转置时，你其实也在做复制。
In fact, in all petroloNpi when you do transpose, you are also doing they will copy.
你不需要复制任何东西。
You don't have to copy anything.
你仍然在共享原始的内存存储。
You are still sharing the original nye storage.
这就是为什么转置非常快，明白了吗？
That's why transpose is super fast, okay?
这一切都是因为这种张量格式，明白吗？
All because of this stress format. Okay.
那我们再做一个例子，好吗？
Then let's do one more, okay?
第三个操作符是你经常用到的一个操作符，好吗？
And the third operator is some operator you use a lot, okay?
广播。
Broadcast.
这种广播操作是你在尝试做乘法或者加法时经常会遇到的，
This broadcast operating is something that you always face when you try to
尤其是当你只有一个维度匹配时，
multiply or when you try to add a race with only one dimensional matched,
但其他两个维度中，一个是高维，另一个是低维。
but the other two dimension proper one is higher dimension and the other is lower dimension.
那你该怎么做呢？神奇的是，当你用numpy操作时，它会自动帮你完成这些。
So how do you do that? And magically, when you do Lum pi, uh, they will do that for you.
当你把这两个张量相乘时，其实在背后会有一个隐式的广播过程，
When you multiply these two tens together, uh, there's an implicit, broadcast
这个过程是在幕后发生的，对吧？
happening behind the scene, right?
但你要怎么实现这种操作呢？
But how you achieve this kind of thing.
一个最基础的方法就是，为了广播第二个张量，
Like one rudimentary way is basically in order to broadcast the second tensor,
你只需要把那一行复制四次，就得到了目标张量。
you just copy the row four times, and you get a target sensor.
但就像我说的，这种方法不好，因为复制操作很慢。
But like I said, it is not good because copy is slow.
我不想复制。而且复制会消耗一些内存。
I don't want to copy. And copy will consume some memory.
好吗？我不想浪费内存。
Okay? I don't want to waste memory.
好吗？我们来想想怎么用stride来实现这个。
Okay? Let's think about how we can achieve this using stress.
我让你们想10秒钟。
I'll let you think about 10 seconds.
好的，有人想回答吗？
Okay. Anyone want to answer?
对，对，没错，就是这样。
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, exactly. Yeah.
我们只需要插入一个stride为零的项。我们来看看这样做的效果。
We just insert one strut that is zero. Let's see how this works.
好吗？
Okay?
那么这里，我们来检查一下原始张量。
So here, let's inspect the original tensor.
原始张量的stride等于1，对吧？
The original tensor has a stress equal to one, right?
因为它是一维的，形状是13，所以这些数据在内存中是顺序排列的，
Because it's one dimensional, and its shape is 13, this data is sequentially in memory,
也就是一、二、三，非常直接。
which is one, two, three, straightforward.
明白了吗？目标张量一的形状基本上是等于三，
Okay? And the target tensor one is basically with a shape or equals for three,
因为我想要前三列。
because I want to furs three columns.
就像我说的，我不想复制数据。
Like I said, I don't want to copy data.
我想要零拷贝。数据应该在内存中保持为一、二、三，只有三个元素。
I want zero copy. The data should be kept in memory as one, two, three, only three elements.
对。那么要怎么修改步幅呢？
Right. So how to basically modify the stress.
记住，步幅的定义基本上就是在那个维度上有多少元素，
So remember the definition of stress is basically like how many elements
我沿着那个维度移动，对吧？
I move along that dimension, right?
所以为了得到那个张量，我要做的基本上就是插入
So in order to get that tensor, what I do is basically I insert
一开始再加一条线程，从零开始，对吧？
one more thread at the beginning at zero, right?
这意味着在我这里添加的这个虚拟维度上，有四个，对吧，就是板载传感器。
That means along the fake dimension I added here four, right, the board carts sensor.
每次我沿着那个维度移动，
Every time I move along that dimension,
我只是在时间零点，然后它会回到起点。
I just time zero, and it will go back to the beginning.
好的，这基本上就是我们在幕后进行这类数组操作的方式。
Okay. That's how we basically do this kind of, uh, array manipulations in behind patters, yeah.
嗯，好了，我要讲的就这些。
Um, okay, that's all I have.
这些操作符实际上非常重要，而且它们都能从压力中受益。
These operators actually are very important and they all benefit from stress.
好的，我们来做一些更硬核的东西。
Okay, let's do something that's more hardcore.
嗯，这里，在某些情况下，
Uh, here, in some cases,
我想交换这些小块。
I want to swap the tiles.
好的，我有一个张量，你可以看到它还是0到15，但我想把粉色部分和蓝色部分交换。
Okay, I have a tensor where you can see it still 0-15, but I want to swap
粉色部分和蓝色部分要怎么交换呢？
the pink part with the blue part, how I do that.
好的。我这里写了一个小程序，你可以看到我的编程其实很笨。
Okay. I wrote a little program here and you can see my programming is pretty stupid.
我需要复制很多东西，
I need to copy a lot of things,
基本上我需要滑动一些张量并交换元素。
I basically need to slide some tensor and swap elements.
我把如何实现零拷贝的方式留给你们思考。
And I will leave to you how to implement this with zero copy.
好吗？我不会直接给你答案，自己想一想吧。
Okay? I'm not going to give you the answer. Think about that. Okay.
但这里重要的是，每当你在Patric里写这种程序时，
But here, the important thing is whenever you write this kind of program in Patric,
你需要考虑自己是不是在做零拷贝。
you need to think about if you are doing zero copy.
如果你能做到零拷贝，就应该总是选择零拷贝，对吧？
If you can't do zero copy, you should always do zero copy, right?
就像我说的，零拷贝就是零开销，你也不需要消耗任何内存。
Like I said, zero copy is zero overhead, and you don't have to consume any memory.
嗯，对吧？
Yeah. Okay?
嗯，到这里，我想我已经介绍完了应力的内容。
Um, with that, I think I finished introducing the stress.
然后我们来想一想，嗯，什么是应力问题？
And then let's think about, um, so what is the problem stress?
我觉得应力问题其实很明显，对吧？
I think the problem stress is quite obvious, right?
比如说，如果我们查看一个张量，或者选择一个张量，或者其他操作，嗯，确实，我们可以得到一个张量，
Uh, say, if we view a tensor or select a tensor or whatever, um, yeah, indeed, we can get a tensor,
但是，由操作符返回的新张量，它的值在内存中
but, uh, the new tensor, returned by the operator, uh, under its values are
已经不是连续的了，对吧？
not continuous in memory anymore, right?
因为只有原始张量在内存中是连续的。
Because only the original tensor is continuous in memory.
一旦我们改变了应力或者其他操作，它就不再是连续的了。
Once we change the stress or whatever, it's not continuous.
但就像我说的，在很多很多情况下，比如按元素操作或者乘法，
But like I said, in many, many, for example, element wise or is multiplication or
在很多其他加速器平台上，当你做这种操作时，
many many other accelerator platforms when you do this kind of operator,
你必须确保张量有连续的存储，对吧？
you have to make sure tensor has a continuous storage, right?
这意味着每次你进行这种操作或操作时，
So which means that every time when you apply this kind of or manipulation.
如果你继续进行下一个操作，而下一个操作对底层存储的连续性有要求，
And if you proceed to next operation and the next Operation, have a requirement on the continuity
你需要做的是，有时候需要调用
of the underlying storage, what do you do is you sometimes need to call
这个操作符 torch 或 contiguous，它基本上会为你重新排列
this operator torch or contiguous, and it will basically rearrange the um,
底层存储。明白了吗？
underlying storage for you. Okay?
所以这个听起来很相似。
So this one sounds similar.
如果你不这样做，你很可能已经犯过很多次这个错误了。
And if you don't do this, you probably made this error many many times in
你不希望抱怨你的张量在内存中不是连续的，
torching you don't want to complain that your tensor is not continuous in memory,
所以我无法进行下一步操作。
so I cannot proceed next operation.
明白了吗？很好。有问题吗？没有。
Okay? Cool. Any question? No.
好的，那我们就完成了这个布局，接下来我们要介绍的基本上是，
Okay, then we finish this layout and so the next thing that we want to introduce is basically,
我们也可以对操作符进行并行化，对吧？
we can also paralyze um, operators, right?
所以在这里，我认为并行化尤其适用于这种操作。
So here, I think the palsiton especially for this kind of operation.
在这里，我希望你还记得这个操作基本上是元素级的，对吧？
So here, I hope you still remember the operation here is basically element we side, right?
我们把A和B相加，然后赋值给
We add A and B and rather to
C。我们是从左到右逐个元素地进行操作，在这种元素级操作中，
C. We do that element by element from left to right, in this kind of element wise operations,
并行化其实非常容易，对吧？
it's very easy to paralyze it, right?
例如，在大多数CPU平台上，你可以使用这个装饰器
For example, in most CPU platforms, you have this decorator
你可以把它装饰在你的循环上，它基本上会把加法操作
which you can decorate on top of your loop, and it will basically split the addition operations to
分配到不同的CPU核心上，并且全部并行执行。
different CPU course and it all perform in parallel.
这里的关键是分区或者说拆分很直接，因为
The key thing here is the partition or the split is straightforward because it
这是逐元素的，每个元素的加法操作彼此独立。
is a element wise at each element, addition is independent from other elements.
所以你可以很容易地拆分这些重复操作。
So you can easily split the repetition.
这是一种非常简单的并行化操作符并利用多核的方法。
This is a very simple way to paralyze operators and leverage mark course.
我们稍后会详细讨论这个问题，因为假设有些操作中，一个元素的
We'll talk more about this because suppose there are some operations where one elements
加法依赖于另一个元素的加法，那我们该如何拆分这些操作符，
add is dependent on another elements add, how can we basically split these operators,
这个部分我们之后会更深入地讲解。
and we are going to dive deeper into that part later.
这基本上就涵盖了我们关于如何并行化算子的讲座内容。
That basically will cover our lecture in how to paralyze the operator.
但这个方法太直接了，所以我把它放在这里。你明白的。
But this one is too straightforward, so I put it here. You understand.
好的。总结一下，我们如何让算子更快，可以进行并行化，我们可以利用
Okay. To summarize how we can make operator faster, we can do arization We can leverage
平台特定的并行化函数，比如load floor four。
the platform specific Corize functions, for example, the load floor four.
好吗？我们还可以操作数据布局。
Okay? We can also manipulate the data layout.
嗯，我们引入了strat格式，这让我们可以为很多很多算子做拷贝。
Um, we introduce the strat format, which allows us to do copy for many, many operators.
对于一些非常简单直接的逐元素算子，我们做非常简单的并行化，好吗。
And for some very simple straightforward animal wise operators, we do very simple parison, okay.
好的。
Okay.
现在，我们进入下一部分，可能也是这次讲座中比较难的部分。
Now, let's go into the next part and probably a difficult part of this lecture.
那么我们要如何让met moo更快。
So how we can make met moo faster.
之前我们谈过数组操作。
Previously, we have to talk about, array manipulations.
我们讲的是元素级操作，但矩阵乘法显然不是动物级操作，
We talk about element wise, but met moo is apparently not animal wise,
你需要将第一个矩阵的行与第二个矩阵的列相乘，
you have to multiply the role of the first matrix of the common second matrix,
并且这不是逐元素进行的。
and it's not performed element by element.
那么我们如何让这些操作变得更快呢？
So how we can make these kind of operators fast.
这非常重要，因为我们知道计算系统基本上就是在做矩阵乘法，对吧？
And this is so important because we know marching system is all about met moo, okay?
一般来说，有两种思路。
Um, there are in general, two ideas.
一种是我们有一些算法可以实现这个，我们会深入讲解这些算法。
One is, we have some algorithm for that, and we are going to dive deep into the algorithm.
另一种是我们可以利用一些更高级的硬件。
The other is we can use some more ace hardware.
这就是为什么我们在本讲最后开始讨论加速器的原因。
That's why we start talking about accelerators, okay, in the final part of this lecture.
好吗？
Okay?
嗯，在我们讨论优化技术之前，什么是Mtmo？
Um, before we talk about the optimization techniques, so what is Mtmo?
好的，本质上代码中的Mthmo是什么？
Okay. What is essentially a Mthmo in code?
我相信你们大多数人都自己实现过Mthmo，对吧？
So I believe most of you have implement Mthmo by yourself, right?
Metamo本质上是一个三层循环，IJK，
Metamo is essentially a a three layer loop, IJK,
这里我们试图将两个矩阵A和B相乘，并且我们试图把结果写入
here we are trying to multiply two matrices A and B, and we try to write the results into
C，它们每一个都是二维的。
C and each of them are two dimensional.
这里我简化了问题，它们的维度都等于N，两个维度都是。
Here, I simplify the problem, their dimension or equal to N, both dimensions.
为了实现这个met mo，我们基本上写这个循环，遍历I、J，
In order to implement this met mo, we basically write this loop we loop over I, J,
然后我们从两个矩阵中取一行和一列，进行操作。
and then we take a row and column from two matrices and we do
做点积然后把结果写回C，对吧？
a dot product and write the result back to C, right?
没有问题，对吗？好的，这个循环的复杂度是多少？
No question, right? Okay. What is the complexity of this loop?
立方，对吧？立方。
Cube, right? A cube.
好的。那么人类社会目前能达到的最佳复杂度是多少？你们知道吗？
Okay. So what is the best complexity the human society can achieve? Do you guys know?
绝对比立方好，因为你们可能知道很多
It's definitely better than cube, because you guys probably know a lot
在这个领域做研究的pH网络专家。
of researchers pH networking in this area.
好的。那么，这里有个数字。
Okay. Yeah. So here's the number.
大约是2.371552，对吧？
It's roughly 2.37 1552. Okay?
但当然没有人能把它降到平方级，对吧？
But no one can reduce it to square, of course, okay?
而且仅仅是复杂度其实非常，非常，我不能说是活跃的，
And mere complexity is actually very, very, um, I wouldn't say active,
但这是一个老的研究方向，对吧？
but old line of research, right?
人们从五六十年前就在做这方面的研究了，明白吗？
People work on that from 50, 60 years ago, okay?
你可以看到，沿着这条线已经发表了很多很多重要的论文。
And you can see, there are many, many notable papers published along the line.
我们就是这样进行这项研究的。
And this is how we do on this research.
你可以看到，最初我们是在立方体这里，然后我们逐渐减少它。
Okay you can see originally we are at cube, right, and we gradually reduce it.
我们试图发明一种算法让它变快。
We try to invent one algorithm to make that fast.
嗯，但你可以看到，Y轴实际上非常细致，
Um, but as you can see, the Y access is actually very fine green,
这意味着它已经趋于饱和了。
which means that it's already saturated.
所以我得出的结论是，metamo 不是一个好的研究领域，因为如果你做这个，
So I conclude that metamo is not a good area to research because if you do this,
你很难发表一篇好的论文。
it's unlikely you can publish a good paper.
好吗？是的，它非常饱和。
Okay? Yeah, it's very saturated.
嗯，但这是我们需要达到的目标，对吧？
Um, but require our goal, okay?
我们试图让记忆更快，对吗？
We try to make memo fast, right?
有两种方法可以让它变快。
There are two ways to make it fast.
我们的最终目标是，对，请说。
Our ultimate goal is, yeah, please.
所以从1990年开始，非常少，非常少。是的。
So from 1990, very little, very little. Yeah.
是的，你可以认为几乎没有区别。
Yeah, you can think there's almost no difference.
尤其是当你把这个放到真实系统中时，那些改进会变得微乎其微。
Especially when you put this into real system, those kind of improvement will diminish.
是的，是的。好的。
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Okay.
我们回到这张幻灯片，好吗？
Let's go back to this slide, okay.
我们的目标是最大化算术强度，对吧？
Our goal maximize arithmetic intensity, right?
显然，这个AI等于计算量除以内存，内存IO。
And apparently this AI equals to compute divided by memory, memory o.
所以这些人基本上在做的事情就是试图增加计算量，
So what these people are doing basically they try to increase the number of the compute,
对吧？让它更快。
right? Make it faster.
好的，好的。就像我说的，它已经饱和了。
Okay. Okay. And like I said, it's saturated.
所以我们得采取另一种方法，对吧？
So we have to take an alternative, right?
我们试着减少IO，这样我们还能让它快一点。
We try to reduce the IOs so we can still make it fast.
明白了吗？
Okay?
这样说有道理吗？整体来看。
Does that make sense? Big picture.
好的，好的。
Okay. Okay.
那么在接下来的课程中，我们将讨论如何让第二项变得更小。
Then in the rest lecture, what are we going to talk about how we can basically make the second term
当我们执行它们时，如何让它更小。
smaller when we perform at them.
好的。
Okay.
嗯，为了讨论这个问题，
Uh, in order to talk about that,
我想提醒你们一下你们在操作系统中学过的内容。
I think I need to remind you of something you learned from operating systems.
好吗？还记得在计算机中，我们有内存层次结构，对吧？
Okay? Remember in computers, we have memory hierarchy, right?
我们之所以有内存层次结构，是因为内存越靠近处理单元就越昂贵，
The reason we have memory hierarchy is because memory becomes more and more expensive,
对吧？越靠近处理单元，内存就越贵。
right when it is closer to the processing units, right?
比如，在处理器中，我们有寄存器。
For example, in the processors, we have registers.
它非常快，极其迅速。
It's super fast, likely fast.
它基本上是本地的，但我们不能做太多，因为成本太高了。
It's basically local, but we cannot make many of them because it's so expensive.
这就是为什么我们要一层又一层地叠加，最终形成了内存层次结构。
That's why we add layers and layers and layers, and we ended up with memory hierarchy.
一个缓存、两个缓存，然后是内存DRAM。
One catch two catch then memory DRM.
那么DRAM之后是什么？
What is behind dram?
是磁盘，对吧？而且磁盘也有不同的类型。
Disks, right? And in discs, we have different kind of disks.
我们有SSD，也有其他类型的磁盘。
We have SSD, we have different kind of disks anyway.
对，好的。但我们不关心那一部分，好吗？
Yeah. Okay. But we don't care about that part, okay?
这里是每一层的大致读取速度和运行速度。
And here, it is a rough speed read run speed for each layer, okay?
但我们想在这个基础上再加一层缓存，好吗？
But we want to put memo on top of this, okay?
显然，这样太复杂了。
So apparently, this is too complicated.
好的，我们要稍微简化一下。
Okay, we are going to simplify a little bit.
我们只有三层。
We only have three layers.
第一层是核心的ALU，对吧？
The first layer is the course ALU, right?
核心在执行计算。
Course which are performing competition.
第二层基本上是那些属于核心本地的存储，
The second layer are basically those storage that are local to the course,
也就是寄存器。
which are basically registers.
明白了吗？第三层是DRAM。
Okay? The third layer is a DRAM.
我们知道这些是计算单元，对吧？
And we know this is computing units, right?
我们也知道寄存器是核心本地的，所以它们就像投资一样，
And we also know registers are local to cross, so they are like to invest,
显然，与寄存器相比，
compared to registers, apparently,
DRAM 太慢了，简直像乌龟一样慢，我们要在这个基础上应用 Mm，看看怎么能做得更好。
DRAM is so slow, it's turtle is slow, we are going to apply Mm on this and see how we can do better.
在我们这么做之前，我还是想提醒你们一下，记得怎么估算 aismont 强度。
Before we do that, I still want to remind you to calculate how to estimate aismont intensity.
我们只需要数一下有多少次读取和写入，还记得这个循环吗，
We just count how many red and reds, still remember this loop,
第一个循环的 aismont 强度是三分之一，第二个是五分之三。
and the aismon intensity of the first loop is 1/3, and the second one is three by five.
因为在第二个循环中我们把操作融合在一起了。
Because in the second loop we fuse operating together.
好的。
Okay.
那么我现在要把 metamol 的三层循环改写成这种格式。
Then I'm going to rewrite the three layer loop of metamol into this format.
我会让你们欣赏这个循环十秒钟，然后我会解释。
I will let you appreciate this loop for 10 seconds, then I'm going to explain.
好的。
Okay.
什么都没变，我只是标注了数组的起始位置。
Nothing changes, but I just noted the origin of the arrays.
So here, uh, I noted that originally the array was stored on DRAM, which is the second layer, if
you remember the memory hierarchy.
In order to perform computer on ALU,
I have to move things from DRAM to ALU to local storage, which is register.
So I have to basically create a tempor storage here and I move things from DRAM to register,
and this will trigger IO ad.
Okay.
That's all. Nothing changes.
Now let's try to count how many ads we did in this loop because this is the most original version,
original flavor of metamo, we basically count how many times we read A read B and how many times
我们写入到C，A、B、C都在DRM上。
we write to C Bet A, B, C are on DRM.
所以当我们统计读取A的次数时，基本上就是看这行代码被执行了多少次。
So when we count the number of times we read A, we basically see how many times
这行代码被执行的次数很容易看出来。
this line was executed and it's pretty easy.
这行代码在三层循环里面，所以是立方次，被执行了立方次，对吧？
This line is inside of this three layer loop, so it's cube, It was executed cube times, okay?
同样地，B也是被执行了立方次。
And similarly for B, it was executed in cube times.
当我们把结果读回来时，你可以看到这行代码是在循环外面的，对吧？
When we read the results back, you can see this line was outside of this loop, right?
因为，我们基本上是把这些结果相乘，得到结果数组C中的一个结果。
Because, yeah, we basically multiply this in order to get one results in
所以我们可以得出结论，就是立方、立方和平方。
the resulting array C. So we can get the readon right which is basically
这样说有道理吗？明白了吗？
in cube and cube and square. Okay?
很好。
Does that make sense? Cool.
这是我们读和红色的数量。
And this is the number of read and red we have.
第二个问题是，我们在这里用了多少空间。
And the second question is, how many space we use here.
当然，我们在dim中用了一些空间，但dim非常大，所以我们不用关心它。
Of course, we use some space in dim, but dim is pretty large, so we don't care about that.
所以我们更关心我们用了多少寄存器。
So we care more about how many registers we use.
从这个循环你可以看到，我们实际上只分配了三个寄存器，
And from this loop, you can see we actually only allocated three registers,
一个用来存储中间值C，另外两个是小的A和B，
one to store the intermediate value C and the other two small ANB,
它们基本上是从dim中读取数据。明白了吗？
which basically read things from dim. Okay?
所以我们用的空间是三个，明白了吗。
So the space we use is three, okay.
基本上读取的代价就是2乘以cube再乘以从
Basically the reading cost is basically two times cube times the speed of moving one element from
dram到寄存器移动一个元素的速度。这就是时间成本。
dram to register. This is the time cost.
这样说清楚了吗？好的。现在我要介绍一个更高级的Mm版本。
Does that make sense? Cool. Now I'm going to introduce a more advanced version of Mm.
抱歉，我好像没明白你的问题。
Sorry. Like I don't think I get the question.
因为原始值存储在DR里，我们必须把它移动到寄存器中。
Because the original value was stored in DR, we have to move it to register.
要手动移动吗？
Move it manually?
是的，我们可以这么做。我稍后会讲这个。
Yeah, we can do that. I will talk about that later.
是的，我觉得你已经发现问题了。
Yeah. I think you already spot point.
这样效率不高。你没必要再移动一次，你可以直接放在那里。
It's not efficient. You don't have to move it once. You can just put it there.
你不用再移动一次，对吧。这就是为什么这里我们只用三个寄存器。
You don't move it again, right. That's why here we only use three registers.
你的情况下，你会用超过三个寄存器，因为下次你还需要移动。
In your case, you are going to use more than three because next time you need to move.
好的，好的。
Okay. Okay.
接下来我要介绍一个非常基础的概念，我希望
Then I'm going to introduce something that is so fundamental that I hope
你们所有人都能理解。
all of you guys can understand?
因为这个概念太基础了，如果你们不理解，
Because this is so fundamental that if you don't understand,
你们就无法理解flash attention，也无法
you are not going to understand the flash attention, and you are not going to
理解所有和attention相关的内容。
understand all the attenon related stuff.
这个叫做寄存器分块元模型。
This is called registered tiled metamor.
这是元模型的一个稍微改进的版本。
This is a slightly improved version of met Mo.
嗯，我会给你们一个非常简短的描述，然后我会给你们10秒钟
Um, and I'm going to give you a very short description, and I'm going to give you 10 seconds
再次体会这个循环。
to appreciate this loop again.
好的，我们要做的基本上就是重新排列原来的三个数组。
Okay. What we do is basically we reship the original three arrays
从二维到四维。
by from the two dimension to four dimension.
这里，我们基本上是引入了两个更小的数，
Here, what we do is basically we introduce two smaller numbers,
绝对比原始维度要小。
definitely smaller than the original dimension.
然后我们告诉数组。
And we tell the array.
我们有很多这种较小的矩阵，对吧？
We have so many of these kind of smaller matrices, right?
然后我们把剩下的维度放在这里。
And we put the rest of dimension here.
好的，这里我们显然引入了三个标识因子。
Okay. And here we apparently introduce three uh telling factors.
V一、V二和V三。
V one, V two and V three.
然后我们要做的是把原来的循环重写成这样。明白吗？
And then what we do is we rewrite the original loop into this. Okay?
我想仔细看看这个循环。
I would like to appreciate this loop a little bit.
我想确保这个循环和我最初写的循环是等价的，可以吗？
I want to make sure that this loop is equivalent to the original loop I wrote, okay?
可以。确实是等价的，为什么这么问？
Okay. Indeed, it's equivalent, why?
因为我们其实是在把原来的备忘录转化为块状备忘录。
Because we are basically transforming the original memo into a block wise memo, here.
每次我都会取一行，这一行的原始行数等于一，
Every time I basically will take a row with the number of original rows equal to one,
然后从这里取一列，这一列在B中的原始列数等于二。
and take a column from here with umber of original columns from B equal to weight two.
然后我有第三个循环，基本上会从左到右、从上到下扫描，
And then I have a third loop which will basically scan from left to right, from top to bottom,
并在这个小块中计算结果，然后把结果写回这个块。
and calculate the results in this small block and write the result back to this block.
这样说有道理吗？酷，酷。
Does that make sense? Cool, cool.
好，现在你明白这个循环了吧？
Okay. Now, you understand this loop, okay?
而且这个循环非常神奇，我们基本上可以再次统计红色的部分，看看会发生什么。
And this loop is so magical that we can basically again, count the red and red and see what happens.
我们首先要做的，就像我们对原始循环所做的一样，
We are going to first, like what we did for the original loop,
我们要统计从DRM到寄存器读取A的次数。
we are going to count how many times we read A from DRM to register.
我觉得这很直接。
I think it's straightforward.
从这行代码可以看出，每次我们都通过way three读取一个大小为一的数组。
So from this line, you can see every time we read array of size one by way three.
我们把它写入这个小数组。
We write it to this small array.
我们只需要统计这行代码被执行了多少次。多少次呢？
We just count how many times we ask you this line. How many times?
第一个循环没有被we one整除。
The first loop is undivided by we one.
第二个没有被way two整除，第三个没有被way three整除，对吧。
Second is undivided by way two, and third is undivided by way three. Right.
我们把这三个都相乘，同时也乘上数组的形状。
We time all these three together, and we also time the shape of the array.
那我们读取了多少次？你可以看到这里的we one会被抵消，对吧？
So how many times we read? You can see this we one will be canceled here, right?
这周的第三个也会被取消。
And this week three will be canceled here.
所以基本上在第二周就是立方体，对吗？
So it's basically cube by week two, right?
你在这里发现了魔法，对吧？
And you found magic here, okay?
但只需要重写这个循环。
But just rewrite the loop.
我已经把读取A的时间从立方体减少到了被第二周的因子除以的程度。
I already reduced the time I read A from cube to a factor that is divided by we two.
明白了吗？有问题吗？很好。
Okay? Any question? Cool.
同样地，我们也可以对B做类似的操作，只需要用
Similarly, we can do that for B, we just time this shape with
循环因子和循环迭代次数相乘，我们就能得到
the loop factors and loop iterations and we get the times
读取B的次数基本上是立方体除以w一。
we read B is basically cubed divided by w one.
我们已经做得很不错了，因为我们已经把B的因子F也减少了。
We're already doing pretty good because we already reduce both BofactorF it's the
结果会从寄存器返回到DRAM，所以它仍然是方形的。
same because results back from register to DRAM, so it's still square.
那么下一个问题是我们在这里用了多少个寄存器？
Then the next question is how many register we use here?
为了统计我们用了多少寄存器，基本上，
So in order to count the lumber register we use, basically,
我们只需要统计在执行这个循环时需要存储多少个中间内存。
we just count how many intermediate memory we need to store when performing this loop.
你可以很容易地看到我们用到的寄存器有这个，这个，还有这个。
And you can easily see the lumber register we use here is this one, this one, and this one.
这个的形状是w1乘以w2。
And this one is of shape way one times w two.
这是w1乘以w3，这是w2乘以w3。
This is we one we three, we two with three.
所以我们用到的寄存器数量就是这个数字。
So lumber register we use is this number.
我们只需要把它们加在一起就可以了，好吗？
We just add them together, okay?
总体来说，你基本上明白这个意思了。
And at a high level, you basically get the point.
这里我们基本上是用空间换时间，对吧？
Here we are basically treating space for time, right?
我们稍微多用了些寄存器，但我们会减少之前的风险，好吗？
And we slightly use more registers, but we will reduce the lumber risk we did, okay?
我们还总结了这里的加法成本是cb的平方除以2加上cb，但我们还想要乘以
And we also summarize the ad cost here is cube by two plus cb did but we want times
从DM到寄存器移动内容的速度。
the speed of moving contents from DM to register.
这个方法已经比之前的循环更好了。
And this is already doing better than the previous loop.
你可以自己验证一下。
And you can verify by yourself.
你可以回去打开C++编辑器，尝试用寄存器循环。
You go back and bring up C plus plus, editor and try to register loops.
你会发现第二种方法实际上比第一种快得多，好吗？
You'll find the second one actually actually much faster than the first one, okay?
是的。
Yeah.
所以这里，为了执行这个循环，
So here, in order to perform this loop,
我需要分配一些寄存器，对吧？
I need to allocate something register, right?
我们只需要看看这个循环，看看我们在哪里分配的。
And we just look at this loop and see where we allocate.
所以在这一行，我们分配了一个形状为w乘way的数组，对吧？
So in this line, we allocate array of shape w by way too, right?
然后在这两行里，我们又分配了另外两个小数组A和B。我们只是把它们加在一起。
And in these two lines, we allocate another small array A and B. We just add them together.
好，明白了吗？很棒。
Okay. Clear? Cool.
好的，在我进入更深入的内容之前。
Okay, before I move into something that's even deeper.
我们先试着理解一下这里发生了什么。
Let's try to understand reveal what's going on here.
好吗？所以你通过看这些术语，首先注意到的是
Okay? So the first thing you noted by looking at these terms, the first thing you notice is you'll
你会发现当我做分块时，其实我引入了
find that when I do telling, actually I introduce I introduced
三个分块因子，我们需要三个。
three tell factors, we want me with three.
但最后的代价和with three无关，对吧？
But it ended up with a cost that is not related to with three, right?
好的，这真的很有趣。
Okay This is something really interesting.
这意味着当
That means that when
我尝试优化这种元模型时，
I try to optimize this kind of metamor,
我可以随意选择with three，这不会影响我的性能。
I can arbitrarily choose with three and that will not affect my performance.
这样说有道理吗？很酷。
Does that make sense? Cool.
我想问的第二个问题是我们如何设定这个值。
The second question I want to ask is how we can set the value for.
显然，我们想要影响很多事情。
Apparently, we want to influence a lot of things.
我影响了我们的速度。
I influence our speed.
显然，我们希望它尽可能大，对吧？
Apparently, we want to be as large as possible, right?
因为否则，嗯，如果它们很大，那么我们的读取量就会变小。
Because otherwise, um, because if they are large, then our read will be smaller.
但我们受到一些约束条件的限制。
But we are subject to constraints.
也就是说，我们的寄存器数量是有限的。
That is, we have limited number of registers.
所以我们受到的约束基本上就是这个数字，
So we are subject to a constraint that is, um, basically, this number,
这一行应该小于ALU CPU中提供的寄存器总数，
this line should be smaller than the total registers offered in ALU CPU,
在核心中这是我们必须要遵守的一个约束，对吧？
right in the core that's one constraint we have to, uh, you know, respect, okay?
我来问一个基本的问题。
Let me ask a fundamental question.
为什么本质上可以通过分配来降低成本？
Why essentially can telling reduce the cost?
是的，从宏观上讲，我们实际上是用空间换IO，但为什么呢？
Yeah, at a high level, yes, we are essentially treat space for IO, but why?
有人能解释一下吗？
Can anyone explain?
是的。没错。
Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
在最初的cube实现中，每次我们尝试执行元素操作时，
In the original cube implementation, every time we try to perform element,
我们都必须把它们从DRAM内存移动到寄存器。
we have to move them from memory from DRAM to register.
但在这里，我们首先移动一个块，然后固定它们，再读取剩下的内容，
But here, we first move a block, but we fix them and we read the rest of
这意味着当我们读取剩下的内容时，实际上我们是在利用之前从DRAM加载到寄存器的数据。
things which means that when we read the rest of things, actually we are using the previous load
希望大家都明白这一点。
from DRAM to register.
这被称为寄存器tut，嗯，明白了吗？
I hope everyone get this one.
好的，我们再深入一点。
This is called register tut Mm, okay?
好吗？你知道，现实并不是这样的。
Okay, let's go deeper.
Okay? So you know, reality is not this right.
实际上，我们并没有三层的内存层级结构。
In reality, we don't have three layers of memory hierarchy.
我们有CPU A，有寄存器，有DRAM，但实际上我们还有另一层，叫做
We have CPU A, we have registered, we have DRAM, but we actually have another layer that is called
LON缓存，我认为LON缓存非常快，非常非常快。
LON catch and I think LON catch is fast, is rapidly fast.
好的。它肯定比DRAM更快。
Okay. It's definitely faster than DRM.
所以实际上，我们可能有三层结构。
Okay. So in reality, we probably have three layers.
那么我们如何实现这一点，如何把元数据
Okay. So how we can make this happen, how we can basically put metma
放在这个内存层级结构之上呢？
on top of this memory hierarchy.
好的。
Okay.
我将介绍另一种称为缓存旁路的技术。
I'm going to introduce another telling technique that is called catch away telling.
嗯，所以这里其实没有什么本质上的不同。
Um, so here, there's nothing significantly different.
好的。我们现在要做的基本上是，不能直接把内容从DRAM移动到寄存器。
Okay. What we do is basically now, we cannot directly move contents from DRAM to register.
我们必须先从DRAM移动到本地缓存，然后再到寄存器。
We have to move from DRAM to LON catch then Oca register.
我们要把这两个循环嵌套在一起。
And we're going to embed these two loops together.
呃，这里我们首先在DRAM和本地缓存之间进行切分。
Uh here we first tell between DRAM and ON catch.
我的切分方式是一样的。
The way I do telling is the same.
嗯，我基本上只在一个维度上切分，可以吗？
Um, I just basically tell one dimension, okay?
我引入了两个参数，B一和B二。
I introduce two parameters B one and B two.
你知道，B三其实无所谓，对吧？
You know, B three doesn't matter, right?
所以我已经解释过B三无所谓。
So I already explained that B three doesn't matter.
我这里就直接把B三设为一了。
I simply said B three as one here.
因为B三不会影响我们的性能。明白吗？
Because B three is not going to, um, influence our performance. Okay.
我基本上做的就是这种翻耕操作。
And what I do is basically, um, I do this kind of tilling.
所以在这里，每次我选择一行，每次我选择一列，然后
So for here, every time I pick up a row for this, every time I pick up a column and then I
我做一个点积运算，尝试得到结果，明白吗？
do a dot program and try to get the results, okay?
这发生在DRAM和RNC缓存之间，你知道，一旦我读取它们，要进行计算，
And this happens between DRAM and RNCchm you know, once I read them, to perform computer,
那个计算不会发生在RN缓存里，所以你仍然需要把内容从O缓存移动到寄存器。
that computer won't happen in RN cache so you still need to move contents from OCach to register.
所以在那一层，你也会执行元操作，但规模要小得多，对吧？
So at that layer, you also perform metam but in a much smaller size, right?
我接下来要做的，就是应用我在前一页介绍的技术，
And what I do is I'm going to apply the technique I just introduced um in the previous slide,
也就是我要做寄存器级的翻耕操作，明白吗？
that is, I'm going to do that register wire telling, okay?
这样说有道理吗？很好。我已经解释过这个了。
Does that make sense? Cool. And this will ended up with, um, so I already explained this.
数据的传输基本上是首先从DRAM开始，然后将内容从DRAM移动到
The data movement passes basically it first starts from DRAM and then move content from DRAM to
一级缓存，然后再从一级缓存移动到寄存器，
L one cache and then one cache to register,
这样就形成了这个循环。
This ended up with this loop.
但在我们进入最终循环之前，好吗？
But before we proceed to the ultimate loop, okay?
我们首先要分析这里的开销，好吗？
We're first analyzing the cost here, okay?
我觉得你们已经明白这个思路了。
And I think you guys already get the idea.
计算DRAM和缓存之间发生了多少次读取其实很容易，对吧？
It's very easy to count how many rates it happens between DRAM and catch, right?
所以为了把A的内容从
So in order to move A's content from
DRAM移动到缓存，我们基本上做的就是，嗯，A在这里发生，对吧？
DRAM to ON CAT what we do is basically, um, A happens here, right?
并且有一个外层循环。
And there's one outer loop.
所以我们只需要用这个数字除以B1，然后再乘以我们移动的形状，
So we just time this number divided by B one, and we time the shape of the we move,
也就是再乘以B1。
which is times B one.
所以在这两层之间发生的内存IO基本上是A的平方，对吧？
So the lumber IO happens between these two layers is basically square for A, right?
那么对于B，我们该怎么做呢？它比A多一个循环。
And here, what do we do for B, it has one more loop compared to A.
那如果我们把这个数量、这个数量、还有这个数量以及数组的形状相乘会发生什么？
So what happens if we time this lumber, this lumber, and this lumber and the shape of the array.
那我们得到的代价就是Nub除以B。
So we get the cost as Nub div by B.
好吗？总成本就是这两个数加在一起。
Okay? And the total cost is The total c is basically, um, these two number together.
正如我所说，你仍然要受到约束条件的限制。
And as I said, you still subject to constraint.
那就是你的L0缓存大小不能超过
That is your LO catch size cannot be greater than
你内核上可用的L1缓存，对吧？
the available L one catch offered on your course, right?
所以你也关心空间问题，我们用到的空间基本上是B一Tison。
So you also care about the space, and the space we use is basically B one Tison
还有B二Timson，然后我们把它们加起来，总和应该小于一个缓存大小。
and B two Timson and we sum them together, and they should be smaller than one catch size.
明白了吗？完全一样的道理。
Okay? Exactly the same thing. Okay.
我只是减少了一个维度。
I just reduce one dimension.
这个没问题吧？好。接下来我们要把这两个循环合并起来。
Good with this one, right? Okay. And then we are going to put these two loops together.
这就是在当今架构中更现实、更实际的实现方式，比如说，
And this is a more realistic more implementation in today's architectures, for example,
在GPU和CPU中，显然这仍然是一个简化版本，因为，
in GPU and CPU, apparently, this is still a simplified version because,
你知道，还是有缓存的，对吧。
you know, there's still to catch, right.
嗯，没错。
Yeah. Okay.
所以在这个循环的外部，我们在做缓存分块，在这个循环内部，
So in the outside of this loop, we are doing, catch a wire telling and inside of this loop,
我们现在是在做寄存器分块，对吧？
we are doing register aware telling, right?
这就是我之前说的。在这里，我们简单地用三个等于一来表示
That's what I said before. And here, we simply said with three equal to
因为我们知道三这个数其实无所谓。
one because we know we three does not matter.
它不会影响性能。
It won't affect performance.
为了让你理解这个循环，我们可以看到在这个框里，基本上我们在做缓存分块
And in order for you to understand this loop, we can see on this box, basically we are doing catch
使用B1和B2，并且把数据从DRAM搬到OCach。
telling using B one and B two, and it moves things from DRAM to OCach.
然后在这个绿色的框里，我们在做寄存器分块，使用V和V2，
And then in this green box, we are doing register telling using V and V two,
我们把数据从一级缓存搬到寄存器。
we are moving things from one to register.
最后，数据都在寄存器里，我们才真正开始计算。
And finally, things are in register, we actually proceed the competition.
好吗？那我们再来分析一下这个代价，好吗？
Okay? And let's try to analyze the cost again, okay?
将数据从dm移动到one的成本可以这样分析，对吧？
The cost of moving things from dm to one can be analyzed in this way, right?
我们大致就是这样来看这个问题的。
We roughly just look at this.
这是我们移动数据的操作。
This is the operation where we move things.
第一项基本上就是移动这个数组的成本。
And the first term is basically moving this array.
这个数组被执行了B一分之一次。
And this array was executed divided by B one times.
每次移动类似这种形状的操作基本上就是把它们相乘。
Very tEveryt excuse it move something in this shape basically time together.
我们就得到了将A从dram移动到one的成本，也就是平方，明白了吗？
And we get the cost of moving things moving A from dram to one, which is square, okay?
类似地，当我们把数据从DRM移动到缓存并移动B时，我们只需要把这个因子、
Similarly, when we move things from DRM to catch and move B, we just time this factor,
这个因子和形状相乘，就可以得到这个数值。
this factor and the shape together and we get this number.
然后我们继续进入内层循环，也可以统计我们移动的次数。
And then we proceed to the inner loop and we can also count uh the times we move
在一个和寄存器之间的事情。
things between one and register.
你可以再三确认。
And you can double check.
这是正确的。好的，这就是这个循环的全部内容。明白吗？
This is correct. Okay. Yeah, that's all we have for this loop. Okay?
你可以看到，实际上这非常复杂，对吧？
And you can see in reality, this is super complicated, right?
那是什么让它变得复杂呢？
So what makes it complicated?
实际操作中，比如在CPU上，我们有从磁盘到DRAM到
So in practice, um, for example, on CPU, we have a disc to dram to
一到一到二到一到寄存器。
one to one to two to one to register.
这意味着我们至少在三个层级之间进行传递。
That means we are doing telling across at least three layers.
也许我们可以忽略磁盘。
Probably we can ignore disc.
这就是让事情变得复杂的原因之一。
That's one thing that makes things complicated.
第二点是，我们需要确定1b2b1、b2c1和C2的取值，
The second thing is, we need to determine the values for 1b2b1,
因为如果你还记得的话，呃，这些分块因子需要受到
b2c1 and C two, Because if you still remember, uh, these telling factors need to be subject to
每一层空间约束的限制。
the space constraints at each layer.
我们不能超过这个限制。
We cannot be more than that.
否则，这个循环就不会运行了，明白吗？
Otherwise, this loop is not going to run, okay?
第三点，你可以让它运行得更快的方法是，
And the third thing that you can make this even faster
当我们从DRM读取数据到L2时，
is when we are reading things from DRM to L two,
比如说，你也可以在读取时进行流水线处理，对吧？
for example, you can also pipeline in the reading, right?
你还可以让CPU读取场景
You can also let the CPU to read scenes
2-1，或者并发地读取到寄存器，这些都可以流水线处理，所以你基本上还能
2-1 or concurrently one to register, and all this can be pipeline, so you can basically even
减少你用来阅读场景的时间，对吧？
reduce the time that you use to read scenes, right?
你在不同的内存层级之间传递内容。
You transfer contents between memory hierarchies.
就像我说的，这些都需要受到L2缓存大小的限制，
And all these, like I said, need to subject to the size of L two,
L1缓存和寄存器也是一样。明白了吗？
L one cache and registers. Okay?
这基本上就讲完了大部分内容，请继续。
That basically finish most of the contents about telling, please.
是的，大多数情况下是这样。
Yeah. Most cases.
是的，是的，请问D是什么？
Yeah. Yeah. Please. D was what?
这是个很好的问题。
That's a really good question.
我不知道，是的，我也不知道。
I don't know. Yeah, I don't know.
我认为那些实现方式关注的是不同的部分。
I think those line of implementation, they focus on different parts.
他们专注于降低计算复杂度，你还记得吗？
They focus on reducing the compute complexity, if you remember.
这种讲解对于减少IO非常关键。
This telling is essential in reducing the IO.
所以从理论上来说它们是可行的，你可以实现更高级的方法，
So they are fungon theoretically, you can implement more advanced method that has
这种方法有更低的复杂度，同时你还可以实现这个。
a lower complexity while you still implement this.
是的，虽然有一些限制，但在Koda中，我认为大多数人仍然采用cube算法。
Yeah, there are some limitations, but in Koda, I think most people still adopt cube algorithm.
嗯，好的，没错。
Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
是的，我们下周会在GPO上再次做这个。
Yeah, we are going to do this on GPO again next week.
那会更加复杂。
And that will be more complicated.
所以一定要花时间理解这些循环。
So make sure you spend time to understand these loops.
好吗？这非常重要。
Okay? This is so essential.
我对此看不到更多内容了。
And I can't see more on this.
好吗？所以Flash Attention基本上就是基于这个的。
Okay? So flash attention is basically based on this.
但在Flash Attention中，我们在那个M的基础上做了什么呢？
But in flash attention, what do we do is on top of that met M we
我们再加上另一个操作符，甚至可以猜到。
add another operator which is even guess.
Softmax。我们只是把softmax和Mtmo放在一起，然后进行运算。
Softmax. We just put softmax and Mtmo together, and we do telling.
这基本上就是Flash Attention。明白了吗？
That's basically flash attention. Okay?
哦。
Oh.
他们就是这样做的。对，对。其实这并不是特别新的东西，但它非常基础。
They, they do this. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. This was not something super new, but it is so fundamental.
对，对，好的，好的。
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Okay.
现在，让我们回顾最后一个问题。
Now, let's review the final question.
为什么讲述有效？讲述之所以有效，基本上是因为你可以重用
While telling works? The reason telling works basically you reuse
一些加载，你们很多人已经明白这一点了。
some loading many of you already understand this.
如果你看一下数学公式的形式，
If you look at the mathematical format of
Met M，你会发现有一些对数组的独立访问。
Met M you'll find that there are some independent access of the array.
所以对数组的访问
So the acess of the array
A 是独立于
A is independent of the dimension of
J B J 只是 B 的一个维度，而 A 没有那个维度。
J B J is only one dimension of B and A does not have that dimension.
你总是可以在其他无关的维度中读取一些内容
You can always read something in the other irrelevant dimension
并且你尝试重用第一个数组中的一些加载，我们可以让 J 维度加一，
and you try to reuse some loading from the first array, we can tell the J dimension by one,
这样就可以让我们重用 A 一次。
and it will enable us reuse of A for one times.
这就是为什么我们可以把负载减少一倍。
That's why we can reduce the load by one times.
好的，好的。完成这个之后，
Okay. Okay. After finishing this,
我要介绍一个非常非常好的作业范例，就是这个。这个非常不错。
I'm going to introduce a very, very good homework candidate, is this. This is pretty good.
这是我当年做作业时完成的
This is what I did for my homework when
当时我在学习机械系统。
I learned machinery systems.
有人能猜到这是什么吗？
Can anyone guess what is?
这是我们大家都很熟悉的一个运算符，就是count two D。好吧。
This is a operator that we all are very familiar with it's count two D. Okay.
count two 本质上是七层循环。
Count two is essentially seven layer loop.
它比metamor复杂得多，好吗？
It's much more complicated metamor, okay?
这是个玩笑，我不会让你们做这个的。
That's a joke. I'm not going to let you do this.
好的。我之所以这样做，是因为当
Okay. The reason I do this is because when
我学到这个count是被选中的那个，对吧？
I learned this count is the chosen one, right?
但当你学到这个时，count并不是被选中的那个。
But when you learn this, count is not the chosen one.
我认为transformer和tenting才是被选中的那个。
I think transformer and tenting is the chosen one.
我会让你用tenting来讲解这个，好吗？
I'm going to let you do this telling for a tenting, okay.
因为这更相关。好的，我们可以稍微
Because it's more relevant. Okay. And we can go through this a little
讲一下，因为我们之后还会讨论这个。
bit because we are going to talk about this later.
但本质上，count two基本上是一个七层循环，你有一个简单的空间循环。
But essentially count two is basically a seven layer loop, and you have a simple spatial loop.
你有一些模板计算循环，还有一个归约循环。
You have some stencil computation loop, and you have a reduction loop.
记住，这个归约循环在met Mol Metaml中也存在，第三个循环基本上就是归约循环。
Remember, this reduction loop also exists in met Mol Metamlthird loop is basically reduction loop,
你还有另一个归约循环。
you have another reduction loop.
但通常这个KH和
But usually this KH and
Kw基本上就是滤波器的大小，所以你不用在意。
Kw is basically the filter size, so you don't care about that.
它太小了，你就直接按原样处理就行。
It's so small that you just do it as it is.
好的。为了说明这一点，呃，你基本上需要讲清楚
Okay. And in order to do telling, uh, you basically need to tell
某些层的循环要针对四层内存层级。
some layer loop against four layer memory hierarchy.
有很多种可能性。
A lot of possibilities.
这真的很难，这也是为什么你知道，当人们做这个的时候，有时候会迷失方向。
And this is really hard and that's why you know, when people do this, you can get lost, sometimes.
好的，酷，酷。
Okay. Cool, cool.
是的，这就是我们的第一课
Yeah, that's our first lesson on
Mtmo 和我希望你能理解这一点，告诉 Mtmooa 这是本次讲座最深奥的部分。
Mtmo and I hope you understand this tell the Mtmooa that's the deepest part of this lecture.
接下来，我们将进入一个非常有趣的内容。
And next, we are going to proceed into something that is really interesting. Okay.
就像我之前说的，制作 Mtmo 的一种方法基本上就是你做这个操作。
So one way, like I said, one way to make Mtmo is basically you do this ting.
另一种方法是你利用 DPU 加速器，
The other way is you utilize DPU accelerators,
这些加速器设备会让这个过程变得非常快。
and those accelerator devices will make this super fast.
接下来我们要理解为什么这样可以让它更快。
And next we are trying to understand why this can make more fast.
那么，这个加速器是如何工作的呢？
Okay, how does that accelerator work, okay?
在我们讨论原因之前，我觉得，从高层次来看，你可能已经知道了。
So before we talk about why, I think, um, at a high level, you probably already know.
本质上，GPU 是在尝试并行化这个循环，对吧？
Essentially GPU is trying to paralyze this loop, right?
而且 GPU 有很多核心，每个核心都可以处理这个循环的不同部分。
And GPU has so many courses that each can work on different part of this loop.
所以本质上和CPU的原理是一样的。
So essentially the same fundamental to CPU.
就像你分配更多的线程，让更多的核心处理不同部分的计算。
Like you allocate more threads, more curs to work on different parts of the competition.
但这个具体是怎么实现的呢？
But how exactly that works?
在介绍GPU之前，我觉得，呃，
Before I introduce GPUS I think, uh,
我需要先提一个你们大多数人应该很熟悉的概念，就是
I need to bring up a concept that most of you should be very familiar with is basically
单指令多数据，对吧？
single instruction, multiple data, right?
这是多核计算、并行计算的核心部分。
That is the, um, um, essential part of multi core computing, parallel computing.
所以在单指令多数据中，嗯，你要做的其实是，
So in single instruction multiple data, um, what you do is essentially,
你有不同的核心，每个核心都会运行同一个程序，
um, you have a different course and each core will ask you the same program,
然后你把数据分配进去。
and you part in the data.
你把数据分给每个核心一部分，然后他们会用同样的程序处理并输出结果，
You give each core a part of the data and you will proceed with the same program and output results,
然后你对结果进行评分，得到最终的结果。
and then you grade results, you get the final results.
好的。因为所有这些核心是一起处理的，而且它们只处理部分数据，
Okay. Because all these course process together and they only take a part of data,
所以你可以享受并行化带来的好处，对吧？也就是加速，好吗？
so you can you enjoy the benefit of paralization, right, which is speed ups, okay?
正如你可能知道的，
And as you probably know,
CPU在这方面并不是很擅长，因为CPU的核心数量有限。
CPO is not pretty good at this because CPU has a limited number of course.
原因是，嗯，原因在于芯片的设计方式，好吗？
The reason is because, um, the reason is how ChiP was designed, okay?
比如，最初我们在设计像CPU这样的芯片时，
Like, originally, we try to in order to design a chip like CPU,
除了计算单元之外，我们还需要放入很多其他组件，对吧？
we need to put a lot of components in addition to compute units, right?
所以我们还需要加入一些控制单元。
So we need to put some control.
比如说，CPU需要理解中间语言，对吧？
For example, CPU needs to understand the IL, okay?
我们还需要加入一些缓存，
We also need to put some catches,
L缓存到缓存。
L cache to cache.
而且我们的面积是有限的，因为我们需要
And we only have a limited area because we need to
让CPU变小，不能消耗太多电力，否则的话，
make CPU small and it cannot consume a lot of power, otherwise, it cannot be
就无法部署在笔记本或手机上，对吧？
deployed on laptop or phones, right?
所以我们在面积上有物理限制。
So we need to have a physical limitation on area.
所以如果你加一些控制，加一些缓存，
So if you put some controls, you put some catches then
你就只剩下那块空白区域可以放交叉点，所以我们在这里放了四个ALER。
you only have that blank area where you can put cross, so we put four ALERs here.
然后人们就试图让它变得越来越快。
Then people try to make this faster and faster faster.
这就是过去20年里发生的事情。
That's what happened in the last 20 years in
硅谷的人们正在制造越来越好的芯片。
Cilic Valley people are making better and better chips.
他们依然能够加入控制和检测机制，但技术进步的地方在于
They are able to still put controls and catches, but where the technology
他们能够制造越来越小的算术逻辑单元（ALU），
advances is basically they are able to make smaller and smaller ALUs that
这些ALU基本上拥有相同的计算能力，但体积更小。
will basically have the same computing power, but much smaller.
因为体积更小，所以你可以在同样的面积里放更多它们。
Because it's much smaller, so you can put more of them in this small area.
这就是为什么CPU会变得更快的原因。
That's why this CPU becomes much faster.
明白了吗？好的。但是在某个阶段，由于物理限制，
Makes sense? Okay. Um, but at some point, due to physical limitation,
我们就无法再进一步缩小ALU的尺寸了，对吧？
we cannot further reduce the size of ALU, right?
所以基本上，我们就是把尺寸从70纳米缩小到60，再到50。
So basically, we are basically reducing it from 70 anomeres to 60 to 50.
这基本上就是价值的历史，对吧？
And this is basically the history of value, right?
在这一点上，我们能做得最好的基本上就是这个，对吧？
And at this point, what we can do best is basically this one, right?
由我们最喜欢的公司苹果制造，他们可以做到300纳米，好吗？
By Apple, our favorite company, and they can do 300 meter, okay?
这意味着你可以在这里放一个三英寸的东西。
That means you can put a three indremere here.
显然，相比之下
And apparently, compared to
你可以放很多70纳米的，对吧？
70 anomere you can put a lot, right?
这就是为什么苹果的芯片这么厉害，对吧？
That's why Apple's chips are so good, right?
好的。但我们做不到更好，因为我们受到物理限制，好吗？
Okay. But we cannot do better because we are subject to physical limitations, okay?
如果你观察这个趋势，你会发现，顺便说一句，这就是摩尔定律，好吗？
So if you observe this trend, you can see, uh, this is Morse law, by the way, okay?
每个人都明白这个。
Everyone understands this.
显然，摩尔定律正在终结。
And apparently Morris law is ending.
嗯，我们无法再缩小ARU的尺寸，所以CPU或类似芯片的计算能力无法再提升。
Uh, we cannot reduce the sight of ARU, so the computing power
你会发现计算能力在某个点上达到了平台期。
of CPUs or similar chips cannot increase anymore.
明白了吗？那么我们该如何突破这个限制呢？
You can see the plateaus at some point.
你可以看到这个平台期其实早在2015年就出现了。
Okay? So how to break this limit.
但事实并非如此。
And you can see this already plateau as 2015.
如果你去查一下，我们的计算能力至今还在提升。
But that's not a reality.
好吗？在我看来，有两种方法，你可以不同意。
If you writing check, our computing power is still increasing today.
欢迎随时发表你的看法。
Okay? There are two ways, in my opinion, you can disagree.
请随意评论。
Okay, feel free to comment.
一种方式基本上就是你进入量子世界，
One way is basically you go to the quantum world,
我会成为管理员，而你尝试开发量子计算，量子计算绝对是
I'll become admin and you try to develop quantum computing, quantum computing is definitely
一个非常活跃的研究领域。
a active area of research.
我觉得在加州大学圣地亚哥分校，有不少实验室在做这个。
I think in UCSD, there are quite a few factory doing this.
但这对我来说太遥远了。
But this is too far away for me.
我想要一些更接近现实的东西，可以吗？
I want something that is closer, okay?
所以另一种方式基本上是我们尝试构建一种叫做专用硬件的东西，好吗？
So the other way is basically we try to build something that is called specialized hardware, okay?
基本上，我们可以把摩尔定律转变为霍恩定律，好吗？
Basically, we can convert the Morse law into horns law, okay?
我会解释这个。这样说有道理吧？
I'm going to explain this. Makes sense, right?
顺便说一下，量子计算是一个非常不错的研究领域。
Okay. By the way, quantum computing is a pretty good area of research.
如果你是一个有耐心的人，你可以在这个领域投资十年，
If you are a person with patients, you can invest into the field for ten years,
也许十年后，即使是非常优秀的东西，也没问题，对吧？
maybe after ten years, even something that's so good, okay?
专用硬件之所以有效，是因为它不是在ALU里加入很多控制、
The reason specialized hardware works that instead of basically putting a lot of controls,
加入很多检测、加入很多非常复杂的逻辑，
putting a lot of catches, putting a lot of very complex logic into the ALU,
我试着让核心稍微简单一点。
I try to simplify the core a little bit.
明白吗？CPO核心据说可以做很多很多事情，比如EFL什么的，等等。
Okay? The CPO core is so was told that it can do many many things like EFLs blah, blah, blah.
但我不在乎那些，因为现在，
But I don't care about that because now,
我只关心机器学习。
I only care about machine learning.
就像我说的，在机器学习领域，
Like I said, in machine learning,
我只关心metmo。
I only care about metmo.
那如果我只做一个只能执行Mtmo的核心怎么样？
So how about I just make course that can only do Mtmo?
但不能做其他事情，对吧？
But nothing else, right?
如果我这样稍微简化一下，我们就可以放很多核心，而且可以让
And if I simplify that a little bit in this way, we can put so many cores and we can make
核心变得更小，这样我们就可以放更多的核心在这里。
the core even smaller and we can put so many cores here.
有两个原因，第一个原因是我们可以让核心变得更小。
Two reasons one reason is because we can make the core much smaller.
第二个原因是我们基本上可以把那些控制单元从主板上移除。
Second is we can basically remove those control units from the board.
所以我们基本上可以利用它们的空间，放越来越多的核心，对吧？
So we can basically take their space and put more and more cores, okay?
对，对，对，计算单元，对。好。
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, computing units, yeah. Okay.
但如果你比较左边和右边的核心，红色的核心其实更笨，
But if you compare the crew on the left and right, the red crew is actually more stupid,
我只能做met mo。
I can only do met mo.
但这没关系。好吧。我们可以让它变得智能，对吧？
But that's fine. Okay. We can make it smart, right?
好的。这是在较低层面上，这基本上就是GPU的工作原理。
Okay. That is at the lower level, this is basically how GPU works.
明白了吗？也正因为如此，从2015年的某个时候开始，
Okay? And because of this, we are basically from some point in 2015,
我们开始大规模生产GPU，对吧？
we started massively manufacturing GPUs, okay?
还有一个值得注意的就是加速器。
And one notable or accelerators. Okay.
而GPU就是一种加速器。
And GPU is one type of accelerator.
所以，嗯，像我刚才说的，基本的想法就是我们使用大量的、但较弱且更
So, um, uh the idea, like I said, is basically use tons we use but weak and more
专业化的设备，并进行大规模数据并行处理，或者说SIMD，这个概念最早在2000年代初由媒体公司推广
specialized and we do massive data parism or SIMD, it was first popularized by media in early 2000
用于视频游戏和图形处理，因为最初他们只在
for video games for graphics because originally, they only find application in
视频游戏中找到应用，因为视频游戏也需要大量的数学运算。
video games because video games, you also do mathmo a lot.
但在某个时候，部署会迅速发展，所以这和部署非常契合，对吧？
But at some point, deploing takes off, so this is fit with deploying pretty well, okay?
媒体在这个领域已经投资了很久，他们还开发了一些软件和
Media has been investing in this area for so long and they also develop some software and
编程语言，让它运行得更快，确保人们可以在其基础上编程。
programming language to make it faster, to make sure people can program on top of it.
我们要学习的一个著名编程语言就是Koda。
One notable programming language we are going to learn is Koda.
这就是Koda的由来。
That's how Koda comes from.
好的，这样说清楚了吗？
Okay. Does that make sense?
很好。嗯，通常你需要上架构课才能学到这些，但在这门课里，
Cool. Um, uh, usually you need to take architectural class to learn this, but in this class, we are
我们将在20分钟内讲完，而且不会讲得特别深入，好吗？
going to cover it in 20 minutes, and we are not going to do super deep, okay.
嗯，不过我还想在这里补充一点。
Um, but I want to add a little bit more here.
通常有三种方式可以构建专用硬件或加速器，
So there are usually type three ways to basically build specialized hardware or accelerators,
接下来我会进行总结。
which I summarize, next.
但在这里，我列出了一些非常著名的，我称之为加速器的东西，好吗。
But here, I list some very, uh famous, uh, what I call accelerator, Okay.
第一个是TPU，你们已经知道谷歌开发了TPU。
The first one, TPU, you already know Google Divided TPU.
谷歌开发TPU的原因很明显，是因为他们想要应对媒体的需求。
The reason Google Divided TPO because they want to pay a media, quite apparently,
TPU是一种加速器，你可以从名字推断出来，
TPU is one type of accelerator and TPU can only do, as you can infer from the lame,
它主要用于张量相关的操作，大多数只是内存操作，好吗？
tensor related operations, mostly just memo, okay?
第二个基本上是，
And the second one is basically,
英伟达正在尝试制造他们下一代的GPU，叫做
Nvidia is trying to manufacture in their next generation GPO is called
B201，B
B 201 feature of B
200的特点是它在某些精度下表现得非常好。
200 is that they can do pretty well on certain precision.
例如，最初我们做的是P 32，在transformer中，我们做的是P 16。
For example, originally we do P 32, in transformer, we do P 16.
这时，媒体说你应该做LP四P八。
At this point, media is saying you should do LP four P eight.
好的。而且专注于精度也是一种专门化，对吧？
Okay. And specializing in precision is also a type of specialization, okay?
第三个，当然是M三。
And the third one, of course, M three.
这就是我们在我的笔记本电脑里有的东西，好吧。
That is what we have in my loft laptop, okay.
它也是一种专用硬件，我们会深入探讨这个，好吗？
It's also a specialized hardware, and we are going to dive deep into that, okay?
简单总结一下，我们今天正在构建的s value，
And to summarize a little bit, so what s value are building today,
主要有三个方向，好吗？
there are major three directions, okay?
第一个是我们尝试
The first one is we try to
首先我们尝试专门化功能，好吗？
First we try to specialize the functionality, okay?
比如说，我们生产的芯片只擅长于元学习，也就是TPU，
For example, we produce chips that are only good at metam that is TPU,
或者只擅长于某种带有稀疏性的计算。
or only good at certain computation with sparsity.
明白了吗？或者我们也可以制造一种不是那么专用，但仍然有专长的芯片。
Okay? Or we can probably make a chip that is not so specialized, but still specialized.
比如说，我可以把CPU和GPU混合在一起，这基本上就是苹果公司在做的事情，对吧？
For example, I can mix CPUs with GPUs, and that is essentially what Apple does, right?
因为如果你看苹果的宣传资料，每次他们发布新笔记本，
Because if you see the marketing material from Apple, every time they release a new laptop,
他们都会说，我有多少多少个核心。
they're saying, I have so many cores.
有些核心非常擅长视频处理。
Some cars are so good at video processing.
有些核心非常适合深度学习。
So cores are good at deep learning.
本质上，他们就是把不同的计算单元组合在一块主板上。
Essentially, they're building different cs together into one board.
明白了吗？就是功能上的专用化。
Okay. Makes sense, right. Functionality specialized.
我称之为这样，好吗？第二种专门化的方法其实就是降低精度，这个我已经提到过了。
I call it. Okay? The second way to specialize is basically reduce precision, I already mentioned.
所以我大概不想……我可以通过用更短的计算方式来加快速度，
So I don't I probably want to I can make it faster by computing on a shorter,
比如采用更短的浮点数表示。
like rate shorter floating point reprendton.
对，这正是媒体公司大力倡导的，对吧？
Yeah. Okay. This is what media is strongly advocating, right?
我记得十年前我学机器学习的时候，人们只用LP32来操作。
And I think ten years ago, when I studied machine learning, people only operate on LP 32.
但现在，最新的模型，比如深度Sik模型，都是用P8来训练的。
But today, the up to date model, for example, the deep sik model with three trained on P eight.
你可以看到精度已经降低了四倍，对吧？
You can see the precision already reduced by four times, okay?
第三种可以专门化硬件的方法，就是你尝试去调整
And the third way you can specialize hardware is you try to tune
板子的分布或配置。
the distribution or configuration of the board.
记得我们做元件布线的时候，会有一些来自硬件的参数。
Remember, when we do met telling, we have a few parameters from the from hardware.
这就是你有多少L1缓存，有多少L2缓存。
That is how many L one cache you have, how many L two cache you have.
你有多少内存，以及你有多少核心。
How many memory you have and how many cores you have.
明白了吗？一般来说，人们需要在这些参数之间寻求平衡。
Okay? In general, people have to try to strike a balance between these parameters.
但在硅谷有一些公司。
But there are companies in Silicon Valley.
他们尝试让硬件专门化。
They try to specialize the hardware.
比如说，他们直接放弃内存。
For example, they just give up memory.
我只造一个只有L1缓存、没有内存的芯片。
I just build a chip with L one cache no memory.
这种芯片在某些任务上表现非常出色。
And this kind of chip can do so well on certain tasks.
这就是你可以让硬件专门化的另一种方式，明白了吗？
That's another way that you can specialize your hardware, Okay?
现在，我要教你一件非常重要的事情，好吗？
Now, I'm going to teach you a very important thing, okay?
你应该能够并且有能力阅读这份表格，
You should be able and you should have the ability to read the sheet,
这是由
product specification provided by
MDia AMD 以及其他芯片公司提供的产品规格，因为我认为这非常重要。
MDia AMD and by whatever chip company because I think it's so important.
这就是为什么sin值被称为正弦值，对吧。
That's why sin value is called siting value, right.
所以这是一份我们将要学习的参数表，明白吗？
So this is a pronoun sheet that we are going to take as is study, okay?
这是由
And this is GPU spec provided by
NVDIa为他们当前的GPU 100系列提供的GPU规格，
NVDIa for their GPU current generating GPU 100,
我的实验室有几块，我的学生们都非常喜欢，明白吗？
my lab has a few, and my students really love that, okay?
通过查看这份参数表，你可以看到，前几条规则，你在说什么？
And by looking at this pronoun sheet, you can see, the first few rules, what are you talking about?
它讲的是这张卡的计算能力，对吧？
It's talking about the computing power of this card, right?
你会注意到，不同核心的计算能力是不同的。
One thing that you notice that the computing power on different cores are different.
这就是为什么有一种核心被称为张量核心。
That's why one core in immediate is called tensor core.
也就是说，他们专门为张量相关的操作，比如矩阵乘法，设计了一个核心。
That means they build a core that is just good for tensor related operations, for example, metamo.
如果我们执行相同类型的精度，比如这里，这两种方式基本上
If we perform the same type of precision, for example, here, both of these two rules basically
都是在32位浮点数上进行计算。
perform competition on 32 bits of floating point.
但如果你使用张量核心，你可以获得接近1000万亿次浮点运算的性能。
But if you use tensor core, you get a number of almost 1,000 Terra flops.
顺便说一下，Terra flops是描述计算能力的单位。
By the way Terra flops is the unit that describe the computing power.
我们稍后会讲到这个。
We are going to cover that later.
基本上，数值越高越好。
But basically number higher is better, o.
但如果你在普通核心上进行计算，你会发现速度慢了十倍。
But if you basically perform the computing on the normal core you can see, it's ten times slower.
这是一种专业化类型。
That's one type of specialization.
好的，GPU。是的，但大多数是中心核心。
Okay. GPU. Yeah, but majority is centerc.
对于这个GPU来说，大部分是中心核心。
For this GPU, the majority is center core.
因为这个GPU是为深度学习制造的。
Because this GPU is manufactured for deep learning.
GPU有不同的类型。
There are different types of GPUs.
它花了相当多的行来描述不同精度下的浮点运算能力。
And it spends quite a few rows to describe, um, uh, the flops that is for different precision.
然后它还会指定一些重要的内容，比如内存带宽。
And then it also specify something that is important, for example, the memory bandwidth.
什么是内存带宽？
What is the memory bandwidth?
基本上就是把数据从GPU的内存移动到缓存或者寄存器。
Yeah, essentially moving things from the GPS memory to catch or to register.
这是我们在进行内存操作时所说的速度指标。
That's the speed term that we applied when we do that memo,
and that number basically determine how fast
it is to move a floating point between memory hierarchy.
One interesting factor is, if you read these flops, you will see all these terms
comes with a star. So what is that star?
It's a very small font, you can see, marketing people really cheating. They're lying.
Okay. The star means with sparsity.
That means if you want to achieve the peak flops, you have to apply a sparsified competon.
Okay? And I don't know why media does this, but this is so confusing, right?
Because when you try to buy a GPU you saw your GPU can achieve 1,000 flops,
but it's only applied with sparsity.
有人知道如果没有稀疏性的话，它有多少吗？
Does anyone know how many it has without sparsity?
什么？对，对。对，只有一半。
Sorry? Yeah, yeah. Yeah, it's only half.
对。如果你在没有稀疏性的情况下计算，只有一半的浮点运算量。
Yeah. If you apply compution without sparsity, it's only half of the flops.
这就是为什么你需要学会如何阅读产品参数。
That's why you need to learn how to read product set.
否则，当你花钱时，你需要明智一点。
Otherwise, when you spend money, you need to be wise.
请。对，我之后会解释这个。
Please. Yeah, I why explain that later.
好的。那么稀疏是什么意思？这就是稀疏性的含义。
Okay. So what does spars mean? This is sparsity means.
我想再欣赏一下这个图表十秒钟，试着
I would like to appreciate this plot again for 10 seconds and try to
找出左边图中的规律。
find the patterns on the left plot.
好的，你发现了什么规律吗？对，没错。
Okay. Any pattern you you found. Yeah, exactly.
在媒体中，如果你能够编写一个始终进行计算的内核或函数，
In media, if you are able to write a kernel or a function, that always perform computation,
但受到一个约束，就是平均来说只有一半的元素，其余的基本上都是空的，
subject to a constraint that is average will only have
那么你基本上就能获得这些浮点运算能力。
half elements and the rest of them are basically empty, then you basically get these flops.
这就是稀疏性的含义，你可以看到这其实很难做到，
That is what sparsity means, you can see this is pretty hard to to do,
至少对我来说，我觉得把我原本的计算转化成
at least for me, I feel it's very hard to convert my original competition into
适应这种方式的东西非常困难。
something that fits into this.
很酷。这就是特别的含义。
Cool. This is specially means.
这基本上呼应了我一开始说的话。
This basically echoes what I said at the beginning.
所以你可以通过一种方式专门化你的硬件，就是让某些核心在
So one way you can specialize your hardware you make some course that is so good at
某种特定的计算类型上表现得非常好。
some type of specified competition.
这就是媒体的作用。
That is what media does.
好的，嗯，为了继续这个案例研究，你还可以看到如果你
Okay, um, to continue this case study, you can also see if you
比较不同精度的计算，呃，峰值浮点运算能力，
compare different precisions the computation, uh, the peak flops,
峰值计算能力也会不同，对吧？
the peak computing power also differ, right?
我们稍后会讨论这个问题，这也是量化的基础。
And we are going to talk about this later, and this is the fundamental for quantization.
那么我们在量化中做的事情，就是尝试对原始精度进行量化，
So what do we do in machinery in quantization is we try to quantize the original precision,
比如说，把FP32一路降到FP8。
for example, FP 32 all the way down to FP eight.
明白了吗？在媒体领域，人们非常喜欢量化的原因就是这个，
Okay? And in media, the reason people really love quantity is because of this,
如果你能够把原始计算量化到更低的精度，
if you are able to quantize your original computation into a lower precision,
你就能从更强大的计算PC浮点运算能力中获益。
you can benefit from more powerful computing PC flops.
它会变得更快。明白吗？为什么会变得更快，其实很好理解，对吧？
It will become faster. Okay? Why it can become faster, is very easy to understand, right?
原来的IP是32位，你需要对32位进行操作，但现在你只需要对8位操作。
So original IP 32, you have to operate on 32 bits, but now you only operate on eight bits.
当然，这样就快了四倍，对吧？
Of course, it's four times faster, right?
好的。但我这里想问一个问题，我不会直接告诉你答案，
Okay. But the question here I want to ask, and I'm not going to give you
就是为什么这在机器学习程序中能起作用。好好想一想，对吧？
answer is why this could work in machine learning programs. Okay, think about that, right?
这很神奇，对吧？因为在很多其他领域，
This is magical, right? Because in many other areas,
也就是不是机器学习的领域，你降低精度，
which is not machine learning, you reduce precision.
你的结果就会出现一些误差，对吧？
You are going to have some errors, right on your results.
是的。但在机器学习中，这样做却能奏效。
Yeah. But in margine learning, this can be made work.
这就是为什么机器学习如此特别。
That's why immerge learning.
有一个很大的领域叫做qtison。
There's such big field called qtison.
好的，明白。我觉得我们把孩子学习的部分讲完了，对吧？
Okay. Cool. I think we finish our kids study one, okay?
下一个学习内容基本上是，我们尝试阅读苹果芯片的产品说明书。
The next study is basically, we try to read the product sheet of Apple silicon.
苹果在搞什么？
What is Apple cooking?
所以这就是苹果在搞的东西，对吧？
So this is what Apple cooking, right?
通过看这个，你其实是在说他们在传达一个信息，
By looking at this, you're basically saying they are conveying a message that
Michip什么都做不了。
Michip can't do anything.
它可以做视频，可以做机器学习，可以做图形，
It can do video, it can do machinery, it can do graphics,
它什么都能做，但苹果是怎么做到的呢？
it can do anything, but how Apple achieves that.
好吗？苹果实现这一点的方式其实是，你可以看到，这是一个……
Okay? The way Apple achieves that is basically, you can see, this is a por okay?
他们会在这个角落放一个16核的CPO。
And they are going to put a 16 core CPO in this corner.
好的。然后在其他区域，这个区域基本上会放一些控制器或者缓存之类的，你不用在意。
Okay. And then for the rest of areas, this area are basically put some control
或者是缓存或者其他什么，你不用关心。
or catches or whatever, you don't care about it.
好的。在下面的区域，他们会放一个40核的GPU。
Okay. And in the area below, what they do is they put a 40 chord GPU.
所以实际上，这个M3 Max就是把一些非常通用的CPU核心
So what happens is essentially this M three Max is mixing some CPU course, which are super versatile
和一些不太通用但在内存操作上非常强大的GPU核心混合在一起。
with some GPU course which are not versatile, but really good at memo.
那么为什么苹果可以做到这一点？
So why Apple can do this?
因为苹果是一家软硬件一体化的公司。
Because Apple is a software hardware company.
所以他们可以优化自己的操作系统，使得如果有
So they can optimize their operating system in a way that if there's something that is
和机器学习或者内存操作相关的任务，我就会把我的程序调度到这些核心上运行。
related with machine learning with Mtmo I'm going to dispatch my program to run on this course.
但如果是一些正常的事情，比如说，发个文档，我要
But if something that is normal, for example, dit a doc, I'm going to
在这里调度这台电脑，对吧。
dispatch the computer here, right.
世界上没有其他人能做到这一点，因为他们无法进行软硬件协同优化，
No one else in the world can do this because they cannot do software,
明白了吗？
hardware co opplementation. Does that make sense?
好的。那我们第二个案例基本就讲完了。希望你觉得有趣。
Okay. Okay. That basically finish our second is study. I hope it's interesting.
好吗？我希望能教你一些关于硅谷的经济学知识，好吗？
Okay? I hope to teach you some economics in Cynic Valley, okay?
是吗？不好意思？
Is it sorry?
是的，英特尔正在研究怎么做，但他们还在追赶中。
Yeah, Intel is studying doing that, but they are catching up.
是的，而且英特尔并不拥有软件层。
Yeah. And also, Intel does not own software layer.
Mac OS 是苹果的，对吧？Windows 是微软的。
Mc OS is Apples, right? Windows is Microsoft.
好的。好的。第三个研究将会结束本次讲座。
Okay. Okay. The third study will wrap up this lecture.
好的。让我们试着看看发生了什么，以及人们在Cynical Valley正在创新些什么。
Okay. Let's try to see what's going on and what people are innovating Cynical Valley.
他们正在尝试如何击败MD和苹果的垄断，对吧？
So what they are trying to how you can beat MD Apple to monopoly, okay?
我相信你们大多数人已经听说过这三家公司，Grock、Cerebrus和Sabava。
I believe most of you already heard about this, um, three companies, Grock, cerebrus and Sabava.
好的。
Okay.
这三家公司基本上都在尝试制造新一代
These are three companies that are basically trying to manufacture a new next generation
非常擅长机器学习的芯片。
of chips that are so good at machine learning.
那么他们在“烹饪”什么呢？
So what are the cooking, Okay?
他们基本上属于我在前面幻灯片中提到的那类公司。
So they basically fall into the sort of category I mentioned in my previous slides.
他们正在尝试调整配置，例如缓存大小、内存等。
They are trying to tune the configurations, for example, catch size, uh, memory, uh,
比如寄存器大小，以确保他们尝试
like register size, to make sure that they try to
找到最适合特定工作负载的组合，比如语言模型推理。
find a combination that works best for certain workloads, for example, language model inference.
明白了吗？如果你看这个性能图表，
Okay? And if you look at this performance chart,
你可以看到Grock生产的芯片在这个工作负载下，
you can see the chips produced by Grock on this workload,
也就是试图从Lama生成tokens，
which is basically trying to generate tokens from Lama,
它的速度几乎比其他芯片快了十倍。
it can achieve almost ten times faster than the rest.
其他公司都是一些终端公司、初创企业，非常有名的那种，好吗？
The rest of companies are some endpoint companies, startups, very famous ones, okay?
但他们都被
But they are bit so hard by
Grogu打得很惨，其他公司都在采用媒体GPU。
Grogu the rest of companies are all adopting media GPUs.
这基本上就是硬件创新的力量。
This is basically the power of reinventing hardware.
好的。我认为你在软件层面上无法实现这一点，但我们仍然会去研究它。
Okay. I don't think you can achieve this on software level, but we're still going to study that
因为这是一个软件课程。
okay because it's a software class.
它之所以能实现这个功能，基本上是因为如果你对比一下Grock卡媒体的产品说明书，
The reason it can achieve this is basically if you compare the product sheet of Grock card media,
你会发现有一个关键的区别，就是有一行叫做SRM。
you will find a key difference that is there's a line called SRM.
什么是RM？好吧，你可能不明白，
What is RM? Okay, fine, you don't understand it because
我下周会教这个内容，但你可以把SRM理解为类似于LON cat的东西。
I'm going to teach that next week, but you can understand SRM as something similar to LON cat.
它基本上是内存层次结构中的一层，但它不是内存，
It's basically a layer in the memory hierarchy, but it's not a memory,
它是比内存快，但比寄存器慢的存储，是中间的一层。
it's faster memory, but it's slower than register. It's a layer there.
如果你对比左边的SRAM，
And if you compare the SRAM says on the left hand side,
你会发现这个GR卡基本上做了一张拥有230兆字节SRM的卡。
you'll find this GR card basically make a card with 230 megabytes of SRM.
但如果你和最新的Idea芯片对比，他们只有164千瓦的SRAM。
But if you compare to the latest idea chip, they only have 164 kilowatt of SRM.
这就是Grock获胜的原因，明白吗？为什么它能赢？
That's how Grock wins, okay. Why it wins?
因为如果我提醒你这个循环，你会发现假设
Because if I remind you about this loop, you will find that suppose
这个寄存器等同于SRAM。
this register is equivalent to SRAM.
你可以想象一下，如果我有一个100兆字节大小的寄存器和
You can imagine if I have a register of size of 100 megabytes versus
100千字节，哪个会更快？
100 kilobyts, which one will be faster.
因为我可以这样安排我的矩阵乘法，
Because I can't tell my matrix multiplication in a way that
其实我甚至不需要移动任何东西。
is I don't need to even move anything actually.
我只需要把所有东西都放进我的寄存器里。
I just put everything in my register.
这就是它如此之快的原因。
That's why it's so fast.
我希望我能让你对这里发生的事情有一个高层次的直观理解。
I hope I give you a high level intuition what's going on here.
好，今天我基本上就讲到这里，但我会给你两个问题，好吗？
Okay, that pretty much is all I have for today, but I'm going to give you two questions. Okay.
第一个问题是，我希望你去研究B100。
The first question is, I want you to study B 100.
你基本上应该按照我
You should basically follow what
今天教你的内容，去学习B100和C的代词表，你知道的，
I teach you today and you try to study the pronoun sheet of B 100 and C. You know,
媒体声称B
media is claiming that B
100正在延续摩尔定律，对吧？
100 is continuing the Morse law, right?
按照摩尔定律，就是说每16个月你的计算能力可以翻倍。
By Mrs law, it means that every 16 months you can double your computing power.
我希望你回答这个问题，B
I want you to answer this question, how B
100相比上一代H100，是如何延续摩尔定律的？
100 continue Morris law compared to the previous generation which is h 100,
还有B 200，这又是新一代产品。
o also B 200, which is another generation.
好的。这里最关键的问题其实是，你知道，OID的股票就是这样的，对吧？
Okay. The ultimate question here is basically, you know, OID stock is like this, right?
就是买它。对吧。好的。
Is buy it. Yeah. Okay.
我的问题是，你已经说了，
And the question I ask is so you already say,
我介绍了经济学、芯片价值的动态，还有人们是如何制造芯片的。
I introduced the economics, the dynamics in sic value, how people manufacture chips.
但你可以看到，有很多公司能做出比OIDiA更好的芯片。
But you can see, there are many companies who can make really better chips than OIDiA.
那么OID的模式是什么呢？
But then what is OID mode?
为什么OID的股票这么好？
Like why OID stock is so good?
对，对，是软件。
Yeah. Yeah, the software.
最主要的就是软件。
One primary is the software.
如果你想更精确一点的话，
And if you want to be more precise,
我认为原因是因为Koda，他们有Koda，而其他芯片没有Koda。
I think the reason is because Koda they have Koda and other chips do not have Koda.
而KODA将会是我们下周的重点。好的。
And KODA will be our next week's focus. Okay.
谢谢。
Thank you.